this is the first of a three video
series about
exercise to plant-based diets have an
impact on Fitness one of the best times
to work out watch the series to find out
[Music]
in my video about comparing vegetarian
and vegan athletic performance endurance
and strength I discussed a 2020 study
that found that vegan athletes even
though they were significantly older had
significantly Superior aerobic capacity
and endurance lasting 25 longer on a
time to exhaust in cycling test the
question
is why one potential mechanism that
could explain the greater level of
endurance performance in vegans may be a
higher amount of carbohydrate intake
which could lead to better endurance
performance through higher muscle
glycogen storage other potential
mechanisms that may explain the better
endurance performance in vegans could be
due to the antioxidant and
anti-inflammatory profiles of their diet
maybe it's even their hearts yet another
study showing Superior VO2 max and vegan
athletes meaning Superior aerobic
capacity this time they also did
echocardiograms looking at their hearts
in real time using ultrasound and the
lower relative wall thickness and better
main ventricle systock and diastolic
function in the vegans are most likely
positive findings now wait a second
given the higher VO2 max reached by the
vegan athletes maybe they were just
better trained than the non-vegan
athletes and that's why their hearts
looked like they were working better
however the weekly training frequency
and running distance were similar in
both groups suggesting benefits even
with the same amount of training so it's
important to educate Healthcare
professionals so they don't try to
discourage a vegan diet it may want to
consider telling folks implementing an
exercise training program to give it a
try but you don't know if it has the
same kind of effects in non-athletes
until you put it to the test of
vegetarian versus convention calorie
restricted diet the effect on physical
fitness in response to aerobic exercise
in patients with type 2 diabetes
diabetics randomized to the same calorie
restriction the same exercise but just
vegetarian versus non-vegetarian they
provided all the meals so they could
ensure compliance and closely monitor
the exercising
VO2 max increased by 12 in the
vegetarian group significantly better
than in the non-vegetarian group who
didn't significantly improve at all
maximal performance increased by 21 in
the vegetarian group again significantly
better than the non-vegetarian group who
didn't significantly improve at all in
other words the results indicated that
more plant-based diets LED more
effectively to Improvement in physical
fitness than less plant-based diets
after the same aerobic exercise program
here's what the graphs look like
significantly better power output and
aerobic capacity and the group that was
randomized to a vegetarian diet
it seems that those eating vegetarian
were able to better burn off
carbohydrates compared to
non-vegetarians and had better insulin
sensitivity both markers of improved
metabolic flexibility meaning the
ability to switch back and forth between
burning sugar and fat besides
physiological mechanisms there may also
be psychological factors they observed
reduced hunger and reduced feelings of
depression in the vegetarian Group which
may have given them a more positive
attitude towards exercise here's the
psychological data those randomized eat
vegetarian had a greater Improvement in
quality of life and mood they felt less
constrained meaning the calorie
restriction didn't seem as burdensome
they had less disinhibition meaning less
tendency to binge and overeat along with
maybe less feelings of hunger
not to mention the superior effects of a
vegetarian diet on body weight glycemic
control blood lipids insulin sensitivity
and oxidative stress
wait better body weight I thought they
were given the same number of calories
yes both diets were ISO caloric the same
calories yet just eating meat free led
to significantly more weight loss about
six pounds more more waste loss A
Slimmer waste lower cholesterol of
course and less superficial fat meaning
the external jiggly fat and most
importantly significantly more visceral
fat loss the most metabolically
dangerous deep belly fat same calories
yet more loss of body fat and not
surprisingly better control of their
diabetes all in addition to Leading more
effectively to improvements in physical
fitness
[Music]
thank you